A Guide to the Village Preservation and Improvement Society, 1885-2023
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Village Preservation and Improvement Society, 1885-2023
Falls Church History Room, Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Record Group 4-8
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Village Preservation and Improvement Society transferred their files to the Mary Riley Styles Public Library by resolution on January 2, 1980.
History
The Society was founded in 1885 as the Village Improvement Society of Falls Church. It was one of hundreds of such societies around the country modeled after the famous Laurel Hill Association of Stockbridge, Massachusetts.
The Society's early objectives were to improve and ornament the streets of Falls Church by planting and cultivating trees, cleaning and repairing the sidewalks, and carrying out other acts to beautify and benefit the culture and prosperity of the village. The Society planted the street trees we see in historic photos, built the first sidewalks, and organized parades and the town-wide July 4th celebrations with baseball and ice cream socials. It helped to start the first library in Falls Church and initiated the first Arbor Day in Virginia (1892).
The Society was renamed in 1923 as the Falls Church Citizens Association and, after a few decades of intermittent activity, it was reestablished in 1965 as the Falls Church Village Preservation and Improvement Society (VPIS). In March 1973 it received Certification of Incorporation from the State Corporation Commission.
VPIS is still an active association. Their website is https://www.vpis.org/.
Scope and Content
Some of the records of the original Society from 1890-1918 are included in addition to the records from 1965 to the present. There are meeting minutes, membership records, with the bulk of the files concerning their projects and their rewards programs.
Arrangement
The early records of the Society were separated into Series 1. File names were retained as they were labeled. Occasionally a file was renamed to more accurately reflect the contents or split into two smaller files. Some loose papers were filed into appropriate folders. In the interests of efficiency files were arranged into series. Files are arranged chronologically or alphabetically, depending on the series.
The newsletter published by VPIS was named the VPIS Newsletter through August 1978; with the November 1978 issue it was changed to The Village Way.
There are also numerous video recordings and publications in the Falls Church Local History Room.
The files were arranged into the following series:
Series 1: Village Improvement Society (1885-1923?)
Series 2: Constitution and Bylaws -- Incorporation
Series 3: Annual Reports
Series 4: Presidents and Boards of Directors
Series 5: Membership
Series 6: Executive Meetings
Series 7: Membership Meetings
Series 8: Financial Reports
Series 9: Committees
Series 10: Correspondence
Series 11: Programs
Series 12: Projects
Series 13: Rewards, Prizes
Series 14: Subject files
Series 15: VPIS Newsletter
Series 16: Village Way
Series 17: Publications
Series 18: Newspaper Clippings
Series 19: Miscellaneous File
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Other record groups of interest are the Historical Commission (Record Group 1-3) and the Citizens for a Better City (Record Group 4-1)
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Series 1: Village Improvement Society
    - 1890-1900 (File 1)
    - 1911-1912 (File 2)
    - Amusements, 1899-1900, 1901, 1902 (File 3)
    - Amusements, 1910 (File 4)
    - Bylaws and Constitution, 1897, 1907 (File 5)
    - Dinners and Dining, First Banquet, March 1, 1901 (File 6)
      [has cards – need envelope]
    - Financial Transactions, 1896-1899 (File 7)
    - Financial Transactions, 1901-1903 (File 8)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, [no date] (File 9)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, 1892 (File 10)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, 1895-1897 (File 11)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, 1897 (File 12)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, 1899 (File 13)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, 1900 (File 14)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations– expenses and contributions, no program, 1901 (File 15)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations– expenses and contributions, no program, 1902 (File 16)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations– expenses and contributions, no program, 1903 (File 17)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations– programs, has a sheet with no date, 1911 (File 18)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations [photograph], 1918 (File 19)
    - Meetings, 1911-1912 (File 20)
    - Projects – East End Well, 1901 (File 21)
    - Projects – Piano, 1899-1900 (File 22)
    - Projects – Sidewalks, 1897-1907 (File 23)
    - Projects – Street Lighting, 1890-1903 (File 24)
    - Projects – Street Signs, 1901-1902 (File 25)
    - Speeches and Addresses, [1910] (File 26)
- (Box 1)
  - Series 2: Constitution and Bylaws
    - Constitution and Bylaws, 1965-1973 (File 1)
    - Incorporation, 1973 (File 2)
    - Resolution Transferring Records, January 2, 1980 (File 3)
- (Box 1)
  - Series 3: Annual Reports
    - Annual Reports, 1966, 1969 (File 1)
    - Annual Reports, 1993-1999 (File 2)
- (Box 1)
  - Series 4: Presidents and Boards of Directors
    - Boards of Directors, 1966-2006 (File 1)
    - Presidents - Mel H. Bolster, 1965 (File 2)
    - Presidents - Elwood H. Street, 1966-1968 (File 3)
    - Presidents - Robert L. Hubbell, 1972 (File 4)
    - Presidents - Louis T. Olom, 1974-1976 (File 5)
    - Presidents - Edward B. Strait, 1979 (File 6)
- (Box 1)
  - Series 5: Membership
    - Membership Campaigns, 1965-1994 (File 1)
    - Membership Lists, 1965-1968 (File 2)
    - Membership Lists, 1969-1971 (File 3)
    - Membership Lists, 1973-1976 (File 4)
    - Membership Lists, 1977-1978 (File 5)
- (Box 2)
  - Series 5: Membership, (continued)
    - Membership Lists, 1979-1980 (File 6)
    - Membership Lists, 1981-1984 (File 7)
    - Membership Lists, 1989, 1998-1999 (File 8)
    - Membership Reports, 1980-1981 (File 9)
  - Series 6: Executive Meetings
    - Executive Meetings (Provisional Committee), March-August 1965 (File 1)
    - Executive Meetings, 1965-1966 (File 2)
    - Executive Meetings, 1966-1967 (File 3)
    - Executive Meetings, 1967-1968 (File 4)
    - Executive Meetings, 1968-1969 (File 5)
    - Executive Meetings, 1969-1970 (File 6)
    - Executive Meetings, 1970-1971 (File 7)
    - Executive Meetings, 1971-1972 (File 8)
    - Executive Meetings, 1972-1973 (File 9)
    - Executive Meetings, 1973-1974 (File 10)
    - Executive Meetings, 1974-1975 (File 11)
    - Executive Meetings, 1975-1976 (File 12)
    - Executive Meetings, 1976-1977 (File 13)
    - Executive Meetings, 1977-1978 (File 14)
    - Executive Meetings, 1978-1979 (File 15)
    - Executive Meetings, 1979-1980 (File 16)
    - Executive Meetings, 1980-1981 (File 17)
    - Executive Meetings, 1981-1982 (File 18)
    - Executive Meetings, 1982-1983 (File 19)
    - Executive Meetings, 1983-1984 (File 20)
    - Executive Meetings, 1984-1985 (File 21)
    - Executive Meetings, 1985-1986 (File 22)
- (Box 3)
  - Series 6: Executive Meetings (continued)
    - Executive Meetings, 1986-1987 (File 23)
    - Executive Meetings, 1987-1988 (File 24)
    - Executive Meetings, 1988-1989 (File 25)
    - Executive Meetings, 1989-1990 (File 26)
    - Executive Meetings, 1993-1994 (File 27)
    - Executive Meetings, 1994-1995 (File 28)
    - Executive Meetings, 1997, 1998 (File 29)
    - Executive Meetings, 1999 (File 30)
    - Executive Meetings, April 13, 2000 (File 31)
  - Series 7: Membership Meetings
    - Spring 1966-1970 (File 1)
    - Spring 1971-1973 (File 2)
    - Spring 1974-1976 (File 3)
    - Spring 1977-1980 (File 4)
    - Spring 1981-1984 (File 5)
    - Spring 1985-1988 (File 6)
    - Fall 1966 - Fall 1979 (File 7)
    - Fall 1980 - Fall 1988 (File 8)
  - Series 8: Financial Reports
    - Financial Reports, 1970-1979 (File 1)
    - Financial Reports, 1980-1984 (File 2)
    - Funds, 1975 (File 3)
    - Taxation Exemption Form, 1974 (File 4)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1982-1983 (File 5)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1987-1988 (File 6)
  - Series 9: Committees
    - Committees, 1966-1985 (File 1)
    - Broad Street Widening, 1981-1985 (File 2)
    - Cable Access, 1984 (File 3)
    - City Hall Information Committee, 1982-1983 (File 4)
- (Box 4)
  - Series 9: Committees (continued)
    - Historical, 1966-1981 (File 5)
    - Historical Committee, Report on Quadrant, 1968-1969 (File 6)
    - Nominating, March 25, 1982 (File 7)
    - Study, 1966, 1970 (File 8)
    - Tree, 1973-1980 (File 9)
  - Series 10: Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1965-1979 (File 1)
    - Correspondence, 1983 (File 2)
  - Series 11: Programs
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, 1982-1999 (File 1)
    - Programs, 1994-1995 (File 2)
    - Programs - Home Concert Series, 1996-1997 (File 3)
    - Tours, 1975-1963 (File 4)
  - Series 12: Projects
    - Annexation, 1966-1969 (File 1)
    - Arbor Day, 1974-1993 (File 2)
    - Attic Treasures Sale -- Financial Statements, 1976-1977 (File 3)
    - Attic Treasures Sale – Flyers, 1969-1990 (File 4)
    - Attic Treasures Sale – Lunch, 1976 (File 5)
    - Attic Treasures Sale – Planning, 1969-1986 (File 6)
    - Attic Treasures Sale – Publicity, 1969-1985 (File 7)
    - Big Chimneys Commemorative Site, 1999 (File 8)
    - Cable Television, 1966 (File 9)
    - Catalog, 1985, 1995 (File 10)
    - Centennial – Planning, 1984-1986 (File 11)
    - Centennial – Publicity, 1985 (File 12)
    - Charter Revision, 1969-1970 (File 13)
    - Cheese Sale, 1973-1978 (File 14)
    - Cherry Hill, 1975-1977 (File 15)
    - Children History Program, February 1987 (File 16)
    - Citizens' Committee for a Low Skyline, 1968 (File 17)
    - City Planning, 1963-1965 (File 18)
    - City Planning, 1966-1967 (File 19)
    - City Planning, 1968 (File 20)
- (Box 5)
  - Series 12: Projects (continued)
    - City Planning, 1969-1970 (File 21)
    - City Planning, 1971 (File 22)
    - City Planning, 1981-1985 (File 23)
    - City Planning, "The Future of the City: Genesis for Progress in Falls Church, North Washington Street," March 1993 (File 24)
    - Cookbook, 1976 (File 25)
    - Cookbook, Hors d'oeuvres at Tranquility, 1985 (File 26)
    - Cycling Paths, 1974-1975 (File 27)
    - Cycling Paths – Landscape, 1975 (File 28)
    - Cycling Paths – Rest Shelter dedicated to Elwood Street, 1979 (File 29)
    - Elizabeth Graham – Memorial Garden, 1987 (File 30)
    - Gage House, 1982 (File 31)
    - George Mason Commemoration, 19914 (File 32)
    - George Mason Memorial, 1975-1976 (File 33)
    - Hangman's Tree, 1968, 1987 (File 34)
    - Historic Houses and Sites – Surveys (File 35)
    - Historic Memorabilia – Surveys, 1968-1969 (File 36)
    - Historical News and Notes (File 37)
    - Landscape Master Plan, 1976-1985 (File 38)
    - Lawton House – Historic Preservation, 1960-1976 (File 39)
    - Lawton House – Park Street Encroachment (has photos), 1965-1967 (File 40)
    - Lawton House Estate Moving Sale, 1978 (File 41)
    - Lifetime Memberships, 1984, 1999 (File 42)
    - Master Plan, 1975-1980 (File 43)
    - Master Plan Review, Downtown-Open Space, 1980-1982 (File 44)
    - Master Plan, 1982-1984 (File 45)
    - Memorial Day Parade, 1999 (File 46)
    - One Hundred Trees for One Hundred Years, 1985-1986 (File 47)
- (Box 6)
  - Series 12: Projects (continued)
    - Ordinances, Municipal – Mixed-Use Redevelopment (MUR), 1999 (File 48)
    - Ordinances, Municipal – Sign, 1966-1969 (File 59)
    - Ordinances, Municipal – Tree Preservation, 1976-1978 (File 50)
    - Planned Unit Developments, 1970-1973 (File 51)
    - Planned Unit Development – Hechinger, 1972 (File 52)
    - Postcards, 1976 (File 53)
    - Presidents' Garden, 1994, 2000 (File 54)
    - Rain Garden, [1999] (File 55)
    - Schools, February 1987 (File 56)
    - Taxation Survey, February 9, 1978 (File 57)
    - Urban Beautification, 1965-1976 (File 58)
    - Walking Tour Brochure, 1974-1975 (File 59)
    - Whitehall, 1978-1983 (File 60)
    - Wine Sale, 1972-1976 (File 61)
  - Series 13: Rewards and Prizes
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1966 (File 1)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1967 (File 2)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1968 (File 3)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1969 (File 4)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1970 (File 5)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1966-1970 (File 6)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1971 (File 7)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1979 (File 8)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1980 (File 9)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1981 (File 10)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1982 (File 11)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1983 (File 12)
    - Awards for Excellence in Design, 1981-1986 (File 13)
    - Business Improvement Awards Program, 1978-1979 (File 14)
    - Certificate of Award, blank form (File 15)
    - Hemlock Tree, November 13, 1980 (File 16)
    - National Capital Area Federation of Garden Clubs, Inc., 1968 (File 17)
    - Noteworthy Tree Awards, 1973-1976 (File 18)
    - Tree City, U.S.A., 1979-1980 (File 19)
- (Box 7)
  - Series 14: Subject Files
    - Achievements, 1966-1970, 1975, 1979, 1980, 1993 (File 1)
    - Central Business District, 1965-1970 (File 2)
    - Falls Church Historical Collection, Mary Riley Styles Public Library, 1985-1986 (File 3)
    - History, 1877-1904 (File 4)
    - History, 1971-1999 (File 5)
    - Issues, 1982-1983 (File 6)
    - Mixed-Use Redevelopment Ordinance, 1998-1999 (File 7)
    - Northern Virginia Recreation and Cultural Authority, 1970 (File 8)
    - Public Relations, 1965, 1868 (File 9)
    - Related Interest Groups - Citizens for Quality Living, 1970-1975 (File 10)
    - Related Interest Groups – Falls Church Historical Commission (Cherry Hill), 1966-1975 (File 11)
    - Report of the Ad Hoc Committee on Historic Preservation, [n.d.] (File 12)
    - Resolution, March 12, 1987 (File 13)
    - Statements, Summary of, 1965-1968 (File 14)
    - Statements to City Council, 1965-1979 (File 15)
    - Statements to City Council, 1980, 1985 (File 16)
    - Stockbridge, Massachusetts, and the Laurel Hill Association, 1985, 1991 (File 17)
    - Trees, 1973-1999 (File 18)
    - Virginia Village Index (File 19)
    - Website, February 1999 (File 20)
  - Series 15: VPIS Newsletter
    - 1967-1970 (File 1)
    - 1971-1972 (File 2)
    - 1973-1975 (File 3)
    - 1976-1978 (File 4)
  - Series 16: The Village Way
    - 1978-1980 (File 1)
- (Box 8)
  - Series 16: The Village Way (continued)
    - 1981-1983 (File 2)
    - 1984-1985 (File 3)
    - 1986-1987 (File 4)
    - 1988-1989 (File 5)
    - 1990-1991 (File 6)
    - 1992-1995 (File 7)
    - 1996-1999 (File 8)
    - 2000-2007 (File 9)
    - 2008-2023 (incomplete) (File 10)
  - Series 17: Publications
    - Publications (File 1)
    - The Village Catalogue, 1995-1996 (File 2)
  - Series 18: Newspaper Clippings
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1963-1977 (File 1)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1983 (File 2)
  - Series 19: Miscellaneous File
    - Miscellaneous papers (File 1)